{
  "reference_number": "2161",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "This is urgent."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "We need to move urgently to protect and preserve, as well as improve on the safety and well-being of our earth and each-other. This\n can't be achieved with any significance by selective intervention such as focusing on one sole part of the emission problem."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "No need to borrow, reduction is the aim all round. If I have understood this correctly."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes but only to move the date closer."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "Yes but please can there be some assurance that an incoming government cannot increase allowances in order for\n companies/corporations to profit."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Exceptional would have to be explicitly explained..."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes but please don't let the economy take precedence over action on emissions. Obviously the economy needs to be one of the\nthings taken into consideration, but not at the expense of global health and safety. Short term economic consideration should not\n\noutweigh long term economic and health and disaster related costs of climate change and damage to our environment."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "NOW PLEASE"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "As a student nurse I can see that the health system needs to be enabled to carry out its functions while sticking to our apparent\n\nprinciple of environmental sustainability. Not only enabled, but loudly encouraged and regulated. Ora Taiao is a worthwhile\norganisation to consult on this."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "Only an independent commission focused primarily on climate change can create effective policy. I don't believe we should be trading\n\nin toxic substances at all."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Please listen to the people of Aotearoa. I am trying to parent my child, nurse sick patients and follow my own dreams, while every day\nmy heart is breaking when fearing for the health of my community, the condition of our beautiful and precious planet and the state of\n\nour sacred waters. I work very hard, and for long hours and then am reduced to tears while walking down the aisles of the\nsupermarket. Because I feel guilty for every single product I buy that I cannot afford/do not have the time to source elsewhere, that\nmay be contributing to the demise of our environment. I am tired of plastic and oil being the ruling powers of our times. It is\n\nexhausting, when you care, to be faced with endless arguments about economics, convenience, capital and freedom to profit. These\nthings will never matter as much as our air, land and water. The health of our souls, minds and bodies. No wonder we are in a state of\n\nmental crisis. We cannot keep ignoring this problem. Thank you so much for creating this stepping stone, and may it be honoured\nwith enough detail and integrity to prevent it becoming lip service and box ticking.\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
